Guide to the Office of Admissions records, 1904-2000 RG0053
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Office of Admissions records
1904-2000
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Office of Admissions
RG0053
9.50 Linear Feet
Collection includes application information, statistics, and promotional brochures.
Restrictions on Access
Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records in Series 2 are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
Series 3 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from Office of Admissions.
Historical Note
The Board of Trustees determines admissions requirements at The George Washington University, and the Admissions Office oversees applications to the University. Admission to GW is selective and highly competitive. In considering applicants, the review includes a comprehensive analysis of the applicant's academic background, including essays, letters of recommendations, test scores, and extracurricular activities.
Before 1929 the Registrar's Office was also responsible for admissions, and it was not until the Supreme Court's Brown vs. Board of Education decision in 1954 that African-Americans were freely admitted. Undergraduate admissions are under the Vice President for Student and Academic Support Services. Graduate admissions are under the control if the individuals schools. The Admissions Office publishes a variety of promotional materials yearly (including videotapes).
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include application information, statistics, and promotional brochures. They range in date from 1904 to 2000, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Director of the Admissions Office.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Office files, Student enrollment and applications, Research and statistics, and Promotional literature.
Washington (D.C.); College applications; Universities and colleges -- Admission; Statistics; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); George Washington University
- Office files, 1904-2000; RG0053 Series 1; 0.50 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains flyers, brochures, correspondence, a handbook, announcements, applications, and posters. They range in date from 1904 to 2000. The materials concern scholarships, fellowships, admission requirements, courses for social service workers, and social science programs, humanities programs, and admissions for veterans after World War II.
  Folders in Box 2 were not part of the original transfer of records, but instead were found by the Office of Enrollment in the summer of 2019. The folders pertain to applications to GW by African Americans and Japanese Americans.
  - Admissions Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Office - Application Forms, 1964-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Admissions Office - Application Forms, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Admissions Office - Correspondence with Boston University - Massachusetts, 1926-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Admissions Office - Correspondence with Duke University - North Carolina, 1948-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Admissions Office - Correspondence with Johns Hopkins University - Maryland, 1938-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Admissions Office - Correspondence with U.S. Military Academy - West Point, New York, 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Admissions Office - Correspondence with U.S. Naval Academy, 1930-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Admissions Office - Entrance Requirements, 1902-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Admissions Office - Recruitment, 1933-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Admissions Office - Student Tour Admissions Representative (STAR) Program Handbook, 1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Humanitites Programs, circa 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scholarships and Fellowships, 1904-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Social Sciences Programs, 1925-08/1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Veterans' Education (Post WWII), 12/1945-09/15/1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - African American applicants, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    General
    Materials were found in the enrollment office in summer 2019. The applications are open for research because the students were not admitted to GW.
  - Japanese applicants, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Student enrollment and application information, 1971-85; RG0053 Series 2; 6 Linear feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
  This series contains documents related to new/transfer student enrollment/application information. The material is dated 1971-85
  - Transfer by College/New from Secondary School Printouts, 09/1982-09/1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New from Secondary School Printout, 09/1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Student Profile Printout, 09/1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transfers by College Final Report, 09/1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Statistics Profile Printout, 09/1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New from High School Final Report Printout, 09/1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - ACT Class Profile Service Reports for Enrolled and Nonenrolled Freshmen, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - ATP Summary Report for Prospective Applicants, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - CEEB Validity Study Service Reports, 09/1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - ATP of the College Board Summary Reports, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Research and statistics, 1973-1980; RG0053 Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains reports, notebooks, and questionnaires related to admissions office research records and statistics. The material is dated 1973-80.
  - Research and Statistics Notebook, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes: reports, Admissions Office research, other GW office research, research done by outside institutions, and questionnaire informaiton)
  - Research and Statistics Notebook, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Research and Statistics Notebook, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Highlights from the ATP Report on the Fall 1979 Freshman Class (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Jersey Statistics, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Promotional literature, 1920-1996; RG0053 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 3, Box 1, Box 2)
  This series contains promotional brochures dated 1920-96.
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures about GWU, 1920-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1946-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Material, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures Oversize, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Office-Promotional Brochures, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Admissions Office Promotional Brochures, unknown date (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Admission Promotional Material, 1968-2010; Series 4 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 10)
  - Application forms, 1970-1999; Series 4 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 11)